Guide to the Eugene O'Neill Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1913-1979; Series II; 2.2; (6 boxes)
  - PLAYS
    - The Fountain. Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, in volume, [circa 1925] (Box 11, Folder 210)
      Inscribed to Kenneth Macgowan, 1936 Dec. Tipped in is "Greenwich Playbill" for production at Greenwich Village Theatre (New York, N.Y.), 1925 Dec 10.
    - The Hairy Ape
      - Film treatment, typescript carbon, [circa 1927] (Box 12, Folder 211)
        With Richard J. Madden Play Company, Inc. binder. With envelope with Robert Sisk's address.
      - Program, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 212)
    - Hughie. Program and clippings, 1969-70 (Box 12, Folder 213)
    - The Iceman Cometh
      - Setting copy, typescript carbon, corrected by Saxe Commins, undated (Box 12, Folder 214-217)
      - Galley proof, corrected by Saxe Commins, n.y. Jan 21-30
      - Plate proof, corrected by Saxe Commins, undated
      - Page proof, corrected by Saxe Commins, undated
      - Page proof (fragments), corrected by Saxe Commins, undated (Box 12, Folder 218)
      - Program and clippings, 1947-1968 (Box 12, Folder 219)
    - Ile. Programs, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 220)
    - Long Day's Journey Into Night. Programs, brochures, press releases, and clipping, 1956-1965 (Box 12, Folder 221-222)
    - Marco Millions. Programs and clippings, 1928-1963, undated (Box 12, Folder 223-224)
    - A Moon for the Misbegotten. Programs, [1953], 1967 (Box 12, Folder 225)
    - The Moon of the Caribbees. Programs, undated (Box 12, Folder 226)
    - More Stately Mansions
      See: Cycle plays, box 11, folders 199-200
    - Mourning Becomes Electra
      - ["The Hunted"], dialogue from Acts II-III, holograph, corrected, undated (Box 13, Folder 227)
      - "The Haunted," later intermediate draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 13, Folder 228-229)
        Signed by EO. "First copy" crossed out on cover.
      - "Homecoming," later draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 13, Folder 230-232)
      - "The Hunted," later draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 13, Folder 233-234)
      - "The Haunted," later draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 13, Folder 235-236)
      - "Homecoming," second galley proof, corrected, in volume, undated (Box 13, Folder 237)
      - "The Hunted," second galley proof, corrected, in volume, undated (Box 13, Folder 238)
      - "The Haunted," second galley proof, corrected, in volume, undated (Box 13, Folder 239)
        With insertions, holograph, laid in.
      - Programs, 1932-1969 (Box 13, Folder 240-241)
      - Clipping of review, 1969 Sep 7 (Box 13, Folder 242)
    - "The Revelation of John the Divine." Annotations, holograph, in The New Testament of Our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ (London: J.M. Dent & Sons Ltd.; New York: E.P. Dutton & Co.), 1917 (Box 14, Folder 243)
      Signed by EO and by James Light.
    - The Rope. Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 14, Folder 244)
      Annotated by Nina Moise.
    - Strange Interlude
      - Galley proof (82-99), corrected [by editor], 1927 Oct 21
      - Galley proof for the limited edition, corrected [by editor], n.y. Jan 23-25
      - Galley proof, corrected, n.y. Oct 19-21
      - Program, [1929 Feb 4] (Box 14, Folder 245)
    - A Touch of the Poet
      See: Cycle plays, box 11, folder 201
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    "Ballad of the Birthday of the Most Gracious of Ladyes"
    - Poem, holograph, signed Poem, typescript carbon, 1913 May 24
      Possibly addressed to Mary A. Clark.
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Clark, Barrett Harper. "Comparison of the Plots or Stories of [Eugene O'Neill's] Strange Interlude and [George Lewys's] The Temple of Pallas-Athenae ," typescript carbon, undated (Box 15, Folder 247)
    - Eaton, Walter Prichard. [Review of Collected Plays of Eugene O'Neill], holograph, corrected, [1925] (Box 15, Folder 248)
    - Hubbard, Frances E. "Of 347 Pequot," article, typescript, 1969 Jul (Box 15, Folder 249)
      With photocopied illustrations.
    - Levy, Martin David. Mourning Becomes Electra (opera)
      Libretto by Henry Butler.
      - Opera treatment, typescript carbon, [1960?] (Box 15, Folder 250)
      - "Notes," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 251)
      - Act I, drafts (fragments), typescript, typescript carbon, and holograph, corrected, 1961, undated (Box 15, Folder 252-253)
      - Act I, very early draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 254)
      - Act I, early draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 255)
      - Act I, early intermediate draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 256)
      - Act I, later intermediate draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 257)
      - Act I, later draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 258)
      - Act I, later draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 259)
      - Act II, Scene 1, drafts, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 260)
      - Act II, Scene 2, drafts, typescript carbon and holograph, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 261)
      - Act II, Scene 3, drafts, typescript carbon and holograph, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 262-263)
      - Act III, drafts (fragments), typescript, corrected, 1964, undated (Box 15, Folder 264)
      - Act III, Scene 1, drafts, typescript carbon and holograph, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 265)
      - Act III, Scene 2, drafts, typescript carbon and holograph, corrected, 1962, undated (Box 15, Folder 266)
      - Advertisement, program, and clipping, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 267)
    - Link, Franz H. "Eugene O'Neill und die Wiedergeburt der Tragödie aus dem Unterbewussten," article, typescript carbon, [196-?] (Box 15, Folder 268)
      With envelope from Link to Norman Holmes Pearson, postmarked 1966 Feb 23.
    - Törnqvist, Egil. "Symbolism in the Plays of Eugene O'Neill," article, typescript carbon, [196-?] (Box 16, Folder 269-274)
    - Usui, Senzo. "Eugene Gladstone O'Neill and the Iwanami Library," article, typescript and typescript carbon, 1947 Jul 19 (Box 16, Folder 275)
    - Victor, Maurice; Raymond D. Adams; and Elliott L. Mancall. "A Restricted Form of Cerebellar Cortical Degeneration Occurring in Alcoholic Patients," article, printed version (photocopy), A.M.A. Archives of Neurology, 1959 Dec (Box 16, Folder 276-277)
      With note of explanation, typescript, from "BP" to Donald Clifford Gallup.
    - Weiss, Elisabeth. "The Dramas of Eugene O'Neill," article, typescript carbon, corrected and signed, in volume, [circa 1930] (Box 16, Folder 278)
- Photographs, 1926-1973; Series III; 0.8; (3 boxes)
  Series III, Photographs, is organized into two subseries: Loose Prints and Scrapbooks.
  - LOOSE PRINTS
    - Eugene O'Neill
      - Sitting on rock writing in notebook, [circa 1893-1894] (copy) (2 prints), undated (Box 17, Folder 279)
        One print inscribed to Carl Van Vechten and one to Fania Marinoff Van Vechten, 1935 Apr.
      - Sitting on porch of Monte Cristo Cottage (New London, Conn.) with James O'Neill, Jr. and James O'Neill, [1898] (copy), undated (Box 17, Folder 280)
        With note from Donald Clifford Gallup to CMO and her annotation, 1961.
      - Studio portrait by De Witt Ward, [192-?] (Box 17, Folder 281)
      - Wearing overcoat and hat, standing in park next to unidentified woman, [192-?] (Box 17, Folder 282)
      - Photograph of plaster bust of Eugene O'Neill by Edmond Thomas Quinn (2 versions), [192-] (Box 17, Folder 283)
      - Belgrade Lakes (Me.)
        - Standing next to Eugene O'Neill, Jr., wearing bathing suits, on dock, [1926] (Box 17, Folder 284)
        - Sitting on dock next to Eugene O'Neill, Jr., wearing bathing suits, [1926]
          Photographed by Agnes Boulton.
      - Home movie in Bermuda Islands, [1927] (Box 18, Folder 285)
        Running time: 6 minutes, 57 seconds.
        Reference copy available.
      - Guéthary (France)
        - Wearing robe, feeding dog, Marco, [1928] (Box 19, Folder 286)
        - Wearing bathing suit, sitting on beach (copy), [1928] (Box 19, Folder 287)
      - Sitting wearing v-neck sweater next to Carlotta Monterey O'Neill in Cap-d'Ail (France)
        - Copy 1, 1929 (Box 19, Folder 288)
        - Copy 2 (copy), [1929] (Box 19, Folder 289)
          Inscribed on back by CMO to Jane and Charles Rubin, 1960 Jan.
      - Château du Plessis (St. Antoine-du- Rocher, Indre et Loire, France)
        - Standing with Carlotta Monterey O'Neill in front of tree (copy), [1929] (Box 19, Folder 290)
          Inscribed by CMO to Jane and Charles Rubin, 1959 Dec 31. Another copy in The Plays of Eugene O'Neill scrapbook, box 19, folder 310.
        - Sitting with Carlotta Monterey O'Neill at end of pool, [1930] (Box 19, Folder 291)
      - Beacon Farm, Northport (N.Y.)
        - Wearing bathing suit, sitting on beach next to Carlotta Monterey O'Neill, looking at her (copy), 1931 [summer] (Box 19, Folder 292)
        - Wearing striped robe, sitting on lawn, reading next to Blemie (copy), 1931 summer (Box 19, Folder 293)
        - Wearing striped robe, lying on lawn, reading next to Blemie, copy 1, [1931 summer] (Box 19, Folder 294)
        - Wearing striped robe, lying on lawn, reading next to Blemie, copy 2 (copy), [1931 summer] (Box 19, Folder 295)
      - Sitting at table outside, eating, at Tao House (Danville, Calif.) (copy), [1941] (Box 19, Folder 296)
      - Photograph by Peter A. Juley & Son, inscribed by Eugene O'Neill to Jane Rubin, of drawing by Mai-Mai Sze of Eugene O'Neill (copy), 1953 Jul (Box 19, Folder 297)
      - Grave at Forest Hills Cemetery (Boston, Mass.) (2 versions), [1969] (Box 19, Folder 298)
        With note from Frances E. Hubbard to Donald Clifford Gallup, [1969 Aug 20].
      - Photograph by Peter A. Juley & Son, inscribed by Jo Mielziner, of 1920 drawing of Eugene O'Neill by Leo Mielziner, undated
    - Other
      - Beacon Farm (Northport, N.Y.). Views (3) by Jerome M. Kornblum of front of house, [1965] (Box 19, Folder 299)
      - Boulton, Agnes. With Shane Rudraighe O'Neill on beach in Provincetown (Mass.), close-up (copy), [192-] (Box 19, Folder 300)
      - Casa Genotta (Sea Island, Ga.). Side of house, with view of water (copy), 1932 (Box 19, Folder 301)
        Inscribed by CMO to Carl Van Vechten, 1936 May 27. With Van Vechten's plate on back.
      - Chaplin, Oona. Standing on walkway in Bermuda Islands, [192-] (Box 19, Folder 302)
      - Ile. Opera version by Dramatiska teatern (Stockholm, Sweden). Three shots, 1958 Oct 28 (Box 19, Folder 303)
      - Long Day's Journey Into Night. Photograph of drawing [as advertisement?] for motion picture, [1962]
      - O'Neill, Carlotta Monterey
        - Portrait by Edward Steichen, sitting, from right, with eyes closed (copy), [1933] (Box 19, Folder 304)
          Inscribed by CMO to Carl Van Vechten, 1933. With Van Vechten's plate on back.
        - Photograph by Peter A. Juley & Son of painting by Abram Poole of Carlotta Monterey O'Neill as Mlle. Clarion in Voltaire in 1922 (copy), undated (Box 19, Folder 305)
      - Silverdene Emblem standing on walkway at Tao House (Danville, Calif.), [1939] (Box 19, Folder 306)
      - Unidentified
        - Man in overcoat and hat standing in park, [192-?] (Box 19, Folder 307)
        - Two men standing in front of house, [192-?] (Box 19, Folder 308)
  - SCRAPBOOKS
    - Photographs of prints in Marion Welch scrapbook (1905 Jun) owned by Henry M. de Mauriac & Mrs. Robert North, Jr., [1973] (Box 19, Folder 309)
      Contains: view of 34 Pequot Avenue (New London, Conn.); EO and MW standing; MW standing in front of steps; MW and EO crouching on lawn; "The Professor (Eugene)" lying in boat; MW and EO sitting in boat; view of "Pequot Ave. from O'Neill's dock"; view of harbor from porch at 325 Pequot Avenue (New London, Conn.); MW wearing tennis outfit; MW and EO standing in front of trees.
    - Photographs pasted into The Plays of Eugene O'Neill (Random House: New York, 1948), 1951 Jul (Box 19, Folder 310)
      Signed by CMO, Boston, 1951 Jul. Contains: EO sitting wearing v-neck sweater next to CMO in Cap-d'Ail (France), 1929; EO wearing checkered sweater on porch, leaning against building, front view, Cap-d'Ail (France), 1929 Feb; EO sitting on balcony, front view, in Las Palmas (Canary Islands), 1931 Mar, inscribed by EO to CMO; EO standing with CMO in front of tree at Château du Plessis, 1929; view of outside of Château du Plessis, 1930.
- Other Material, 1912-1993; Series IV; 0.8; (3 boxes)
  Series IV, Other Material, is organized into two subseries: Legal Material and Other.
  - LEGAL MATERIAL
    - Agreement between Carlotta Monterey O'Neill and Yale University regarding Long Day's Journey Into Night, 1955 May 27 (Box 20, Folder 311)
    - Agreement between Eugene O'Neill and Intercontinental Theatre Arts Bureau regarding Strange Interlude, 1950 Nov 15 (Box 20, Folder 312)
    - Agreement between Art Selwyn and Kenneth Macgowan regarding Welded, 1924 Feb 4 (Box 20, Folder 313)
      Signed by Selwyn and Macgowan. With three contracts, one each between Macgowan and: Jacob Ben-Ami, Robert Edmond Jones, and Stark Young.
    - Agreement between Harry Weinberger and James Light regarding production of Eugene O'Neill's plays, 1923 Mar (Box 20, Folder 314)
      With two receipts and one credit from Boni & Liveright for O'Neill's books purchased by Weinberger.
    - Documents regarding divorce from Kathleen Pitt-Smith, and child support for Eugene O'Neill, Jr., 1912-1921 (Box 20, Folder 315)
    - Documents retaining Harry Weinberger as attorney, 1928-1930 (Box 20, Folder 316)
    - Documents transferring rights to Eugene O'Neill's plays to Carlotta Monterey O'Neill, 1952 Mar 3 (Box 20, Folder 317)
    - Receipt from Canada. Library of Parliament to Burns & MacEachern for Long Day's Journey Into Night, 1956 Feb 14 (Box 20, Folder 318)
    - Wills, 1947-1951 (Box 20, Folder 319-320)
  - OTHER
    - Crouse, Russel. "Excerpts from the Diaries of Russel Crouse" [regarding Eugene O'Neill and Carlotta Monterey O'Neill], typescript, typescript carbon, and typescript (photocopy), 1944-1953 (Box 21, Folder 321)
      With notes, holograph, on telephone calls regarding the O'Neills.
    - Fitzgerald, M. Eleanor. Memorial brochure for, 1955 (Box 21, Folder 322)
    - Legassie, N. W. [Eugene O'Neill sitting on rock writing in notebook, circa 1893-1894], statue, bronze, [1993] (Box 21, Folder 323)
    - O'Neill, Carlotta Monterey. Engagement calendar, 1958 (Box 21, Folder 324)
      With bill for The Lowell, 1958 Aug and telegram from José Quintero, 1958 Sep 7. One sheet of notes laid in week of 1958 Jun 15.
    - O'Neill, Eugene
      - Biographical clippings and brochures, 1923-1960 (Box 21, Folder 325-337)
      - Biographical clippings and brochures, 1961-1970, undated (Box 22, Folder 338-343)
      - United States Post Office Dept. stamp, in program, 1967 Oct 16 (Box 22, Folder 344)
        With press release of remarks given by Ronald B. Lee, New London, Conn.
    - O'Neill, James
      - Bronze printing plate of James O'Neill as Antony in "Julius Caesar", undated (Box 22, Folder 344a)
- 2011 Addition, 1951; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series V. 2011 Addition contains photocopies of letters from Eugene and Carlotta O'Neill to Kenneth Macgowan, along with four autograph manuscript letters, signed and dated 1951, from Carlotta.
  - EUGENE O'NEILL CORRESPONDENCE
    - Macgowan, Kenneth
      - Correspondence (photocopies), undated; 4 (Box 28 / Folder 418-421)
  - CARLOTTA MONTEREY O'NEILL CORRESPONDENCE
    - Macgowan, Kenneth, 1951
      - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 28 / Folder 422)
      - Correspondence (photocopies), undated; 2 (Box 28 / Folder 423-424)
- 2015 Addition, 1921-1964; Series VI; 0.42; 1 box
  Series VI. 2015 Addition contains Proofs of Mourning Becomes Electra, dated 1931, and a letter from Eugene O'Neill to the editor of the Yale Daily News, dated 1921.
  - Mourning Becomes Electra
    - Second proofs of Mourning Becomes Electra, Parts I-III, with autograph manuscript corrections by O'Neill and others, 1931; 3 (Box 29, Folder 425-427)
  - Eugene O'Neill Letter to Bromwell Ault
    - Autograph letter signed, dated April 15, 1921, from Eugene O'Neill to the editor of the Yale Daily News [Bromwell Ault, Sr.], 1921-1964; 3 (Box 30, Folder 428-430)
      Includes photograph of Eugene O'Neill by Carl Van Vechten, and typed note, signed by Bromwell Ault, Jr., dated June 11, 1964, regarding the letter.
- Oversize, 2; (1 box) + 4 broadside folders
  - The Iceman Cometh
    - Galley proof, corrected [by editor?] (in Series II), n.y. Jan 21-30 (Box 23, Folder 345)
    - Page proof, corrected [by editor?] (in Series II), undated (Box 23, Folder 346)
  - Strange Interlude
    - Galley proof (82-99), corrected [by editor] (in Series II), 1927 Oct 21 (Box 23, Folder 347)
    - Galley proof for the limited edition, corrected [by editor] (in Series II), n.y. Jan 23-25 (Box 23, Folder 348)
    - Galley proof, corrected (in Series II), n.y. Oct 19-21 (Box 23, Folder 349)
  - Cycle plays. More Stately Mansions. Clipping of review (in Series II), 1967 Oct 13 (Box Bsd, folder 350)
  - The Iceman Cometh. Plate proof, corrected by Saxe Commins (in Series II) (Box Bsd, folder 351)
  - Photograph by Peter A. Juley & Son, inscribed by Jo Mielziner, of 1920 drawing of Eugene O'Neill by Leo Mielziner (in Series III), undated (Box Bsd, folder 352)
  - Long Day's Journey Into Night. Photograph of drawing [as advertisement?] for motion picture (in Series III), [1962] (Box Bsd, folder 353)
  - Diff'rent. Draft, typescript carbon and holograph, in notebook (in Series II), undated (Box 27, Folder 417)
- Restricted Fragile, 1.6; (3 boxes)
  Boxes 24-26, Restricted Fragile, contain fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order and may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints have been substituted in the main files for reference use.
  - Box 1, folders 1-2 (Box 24, Folder 354)
  - Box 1, folders 4-6, 10, 13 (Box 24, Folder 355)
  - Box 2, folders 16-17, 19 (Box 24, Folder 356)
  - Box 2, folder 22 (Box 24, Folder 357)
  - Box 2, folder 26 (Box 24, Folder 358)
  - Box 2, folder 27 (Box 24, Folder 358a)
  - Box 2, folder 28 (Box 24, Folder 359)
  - Box 2, folders 35, 37 (Box 24, Folder 360)
  - Box 2, folders 38-40; Box 3, folders 43-46 (Box 24, Folder 361)
  - Box 3, folders 49-51 (Box 24, Folder 362)
  - Box 3, folder 59 (Box 24, Folder 363)
  - Box 3, folder 60 (Box 24, Folder 364)
  - Box 4, folders 61-62 (Box 24, Folder 365)
  - Box 4, folder 74 (Box 24, Folder 366)
  - Box 5, folders 75, 79, 83 (Box 24, Folder 367)
  - Box 5, folder 88; Box 6, folder 98 (Box 24, Folder 368)
  - Box 7, folders 111-113 (Box 24, Folder 369)
  - Box 7, folders 114-116 (Box 24, Folder 370)
  - Box 7, folders 117-119 (Box 24, Folder 371)
  - Box 8, folders 128-129 (Box 24, Folder 372)
  - Box 8, folders 133-135 (Box 24, Folder 373)
  - Box 8, folder 137 (Box 24, Folder 374)
  - Box 8, folder 140 (Box 24, Folder 375)
  - Box 9, folder 152 (Box 24, Folder 376)
  - Box 9, folder 155 (Box 24, Folder 377)
  - Box 10, folder 167 (Box 24, Folder 378)
  - Box 10, folder 169 (Box 24, Folder 379)
  - Box 10, folder 170 (Box 24, Folder 380)
  - Box 10, folder 171 (Box 24, Folder 381)
  - Box 10, folder 184 (Box 24, Folder 382)
  - Box 10, folders 187-188 (Box 24, Folder 383)
  - Box 10, folders 191-192 (Box 24, Folder 384)
  - Box 10, folder 193 (Box 24, Folder 385)
  - Box 11, folder 195 (Box 24, Folder 386)
  - Box 11, folder 196 (Box 24, Folder 387)
  - Box 11, folder 198 (Box 24, Folder 388)
  - Box 11, folder 201 (Box 24, Folder 389)
  - Box 12, folder 213 (Box 24, Folder 390)
  - Box 12, folder 219 (Box 24, Folder 391)
  - Box 12, folder 221 (Box 24, Folder 392)
  - Box 12, folder 224 (Box 24, Folder 393)
  - Box 13, folder 227 (Box 24, Folder 394)
  - Box 13, folder 239 (Box 24, Folder 395)
  - Box 13, folder 241 (Box 24, Folder 396)
  - Box 15, folder 249 (Box 25, Folder 397)
  - Box 15, folder 251 (Box 25, Folder 398)
  - Box 15, folder 252 (Box 25, Folder 399)
  - Box 15, folder 253 (Box 25, Folder 400)
  - Box 15, folder 254 (Box 25, Folder 401)
  - Box 15, folder 255 (Box 25, Folder 402)
  - Box 15, folder 256 (Box 25, Folder 403)
  - Box 15, folder 257 (Box 25, Folder 404)
  - Box 15, folder 259 (Box 25, Folder 405)
  - Box 15, folder 260 (Box 25, Folder 406)
  - Box 15, folder 261 (Box 25, Folder 407)
  - Box 15, folder 262 (Box 25, Folder 408)
  - Box 15, folder 264 (Box 25, Folder 409)
  - Box 15, folder 265 (Box 25, Folder 410)
  - Box 15, folder 266 (Box 25, Folder 411)
  - Box 17, folder 280 (Box 25, Folder 412)
  - Box 17, folder 281 (Box 25, Folder 413)
  - Box 21, folder 321 (Box 25, Folder 414)
  - Box 18, folder 285 (Box 26, Folder 415)
  - Box 21, folder 323 (Box Art, Folder 416)